Dell H. Hymes Papers 1947-1992 Mss.Ms.Coll.55
American Philosophical Society
- Series III. Works by Hymes, 1947-1987; 3 lin. feet (Box 57-62)
  - Works by Hymes, Hymes, Dell H.
    - Forward to "Portraits of 'the Whiteman'" by Keith Basso, 1978-1979
    - Forward to "Telling Tongues; Language policy in Mexico, colony to nation." By Shirley Brice Heath., 1972
    - Humanities in Society. "A Comment on 'Humanistic Professions.'", [1978]
    - In Five-Year Patterns., 1979
    - "Intellectual Autobiography", n.d.
    - "Interpretation of a Tonkawa Paradigm.", [1965]
    - International Journal of American Linguistics. "How to talk like a Bear in Takelma", April,1978
    - International Journal of the Sociology of Language. "A Pattern of Verbal Irony in Chinookan.", 1987
    - International Journal of the Sociology of Language. "Sociolinguistics: Stability and Consolidation.", 1983
    - Journal of Social Issues. "Models of the Interaction of Language and Social Setting.", 1967
    - Key to Jacobs' Clackamas Notebooks. Appendix V., 1977
    - "Linguistic Aspects of Comparative Political Research." in The Methodology of Comparative Research by Robert T. Holt and John E. Turner. (eds.), 1969
    - Linguistic Institute Conference on Linguistic Method. "Linguistic Method of Ethnography", 1966
    - "Linguistic Method in Ethnography." in Method and Theory in Linguistics, edited by Paul L. Garvin., 1964
    - Linguistic Method in Ethnography, its development in the United States., [1970]
    - "Linguistic Problems in Defining the Concept of 'Tribe'"
    - Notes for talk at Temple [University] Student Forum. "Professionalism & Relevance in Anthropology.", 9 April 1970
    - Notes on Bibliography of Morris Swadesh, n.d.
    - Notes on Book Reviews. "Universals of Language." "Word and Object", 1963
    - Notes on "Ethnography of Speaking" and "Functions.. ."
    - Notes on "Linguistic Method of Ethnography", 1966
    - Notes on the talk "On the Role of Marxism in American Anthropology", 1965
    - Notes. Various works., 1968-1969, n.d.
    - Obituary. Alfred Louis Kroeber. with notes., 1961
    - Obituary. Morris Swadesh. with notes., 1970
    - Origin and Diversification of Language. By Morris Swadesh. Edited by Joel Sherzer. "Introduction", 1971
    - Poems., 1987
    - Preface to "Languages of the West Indies" by Douglas Taylor. With Sidney Mintz., 1975
    - Quadrant Seminar in Linguistic Anthropology., 1967
    - "Qualitative/Quantitative Research Methodologies in Education: A linguistic perspective"., n.d.
    - "Reading Clackamas Texts" for Traditional Literatures of the American Indian by Karl Koeber., 1981
    - Reinventing Anthropology. "Introduction" "Precis" with notes., 1971
    - Reinventing Anthropology. "Notes on Contributors", 1972
    - "Reinventing Anthropology: Response to Kaplan and Donald."
    - Report on Burg Wartenstein Symposium No.18. "The Use of Computers in Anthropology.", 1962
    - Report on "Wintu Grammar" by Harvey Pitkin., 1978
    - "Secondary Significance of gender in a Wishram text."
    - Site Visit Report on the Department of Anthropology, Columbia University. With Aram A. Yengoyan and David Pilbeam., 1978
    - Social Anthropology and Language. "Sociolinguisticsand the Ethnography of Speaking", 1968-1971
    - Social Science Research Council. Application for Fellowship., 1954
    - "Some Notes on Speaking", 1967
    - "Some Quotations from the Tradition.", 1974
    - Some Stories of the People of Warm Springs Reservation as told in Wasco by Hiram Smith., 1967
    - Speech by Philip Kahelamet., 1956
    - Statement of Dell Hymes., 20 March 1971
    - Studies in Southwestern Ethnolinguistics. With William E. Bittle. "Preface" "Notes" "Maps", [1967]
    - Studies in the History of Linguistics. "Introduction", n.d.
    - Studies in the History of Linguistics. "Preface" "Contents", 1967-1971
    - Terms for Relatives in Wasco. Appendix IV., 1978
    - Theory and Society. Book Reviews, 1982-1986
    - Theory and Society. Comment on "Ethnomethodology and Structuralism" by Charles C. Lemert., 1977-1978
    - Twenty-Third Annual Horace Mann Lecture. "Language in Education: Forward to Fundamentals.", 13 May 1976
    - UCLA Sociolinguistics Conference. "Two Types of Linguistic Relativity: Some Examples from AmerIndian Ethnography", 1964
    - University of Pennsylvania. Linguistic Course Notes., 1965-1969
    - University of Pennsylvania. "Notes on Ethnography and Education at GSE", 1977
    - Unknown Linguistic Notes., n.d.
    - Warm Springs Sahaptin. Word & Phrase list., 1976
    - Wasco Dictionary Principles. Appendix I., 1976
    - Wasco Semantic Domains. (First version) Appendix III., [1976]
- Series IV. Works by Others, 1951-1987; 2 lin. feet (Box 63-66)
  Articles, notes, and papers written by colleagues and students of Hymes. Arranged alphabetically by author then title. Note: see also, Series I under name of correspondent for more works by others.
  - "The Tradition of Condillac: The Origin of Language in the Eighteenth Century and the Debate in the Berlin Academy before Herder", [1969]; Aarsleff, Hans
  - "Cultural Conservation and Language: America's many Voices" proposal., 1987; Abrams, Roger.
  - "Observations on the Dilemmas and Ethics of Anthropological Inquiry", [1971]; Appell, George N.
  - "Learning about Culture" History of Anthropology., [1983]; Barnett, H.G.
  - "Black English Style Shifting", n.d.; Baugh, John
  - "Formal Refinement of the Notion for Rules within the Labovian Variable Paradigm", n.d.; Baugh, John
  - "Linguistic Characteristics of Afro-American Ethnicity Detection: Targets for the Acquisition of Standard English", Baugh, John
  - "The Social Stratification of Black and Hispanic English", Baugh, John
  - "A Survey of Afro-American English", n.d.; Baugh, John
  - "Seminar Description", n.d.
  - "Selected Poetry", 1955-1970; Berntsen, Maxine.
  - "The Construction of an Empirically based Mathematically derived Classification System", 1962; Borko, Harold.
  - "The Social Act of Writing", 1982; Brodkey, Linda.
  - "The Song beyond the Song: The Social Aesthetics of Greek Folk Song", Caraveli, Anna.
  - "Cinema Naivete: a Sociovidistic Approach to the Home-Mode of Visual Communication", 1972; Chalfen, Richard.
  - "The Fed-Up Hopi: Resistance of the American Indian an the Silence of the Good Anthropologists", 1969; Clemmer, Richard O.
  - "Code-Switching in Cross-Status Communication", 1969; Corsaro, William A.
  - "Computer Analysis of Archaeological Data from Teotihuacan, Mexico", 1965; Cowgill, George.
  - "Computers and Prehistoric Archaeology", [1965]; Cowgill, George.
  - "Reply" to Relevance., n.d.; Dalton, George.
  - "Introduction to Linguistic Anthropology", n.d.; Darnell, Regna and Anthony L. Vanek.
  - "On the Desirability and Feasibility of Establishing a National Archive of American Linguistics History", 1979; Davis, Boyd and Ray O'Cain.
  - "On the Re-Integration of Linguistics and Psychology", 1976; Derwing, Bruce L. and William J. Baker.
  - "Anti-Kaplan: Defining the Marxist Tradition", Diamond, Stanley, Bob Scholte and Eric Wolf.
  - "Epilogue" for Reinventing Anthropology., [1972]; Diamond, Stanley
  - "Totems" poems., 1981; Diamond, Stanley
  - "The Foundation of Comparative Linguistics: Revolution or Continuation?", [1974]; Diderichsen, Paul.
  - "Women as Placemakers: Architecture and Language Use in the Nomadic African Context", 1984; Eastman, Carol.
  - "Aspects of Kaluli Musical Theory", 1980; Feld, Steven.
  - "Poetic Grammar as Symbolic Persuasion: Language in Kaluli Expressive Style", 1979; Feld, Steven.
  - "Pilot Project in Child Phonology Archiving", [1978]; Ferguson, Charles A.
  - "Small Groups and the Creation of Culture: Determinants of the Development of Idioculture", [1983]; Fine, Gary Alan.
  - "Epilogue" for American Structuralism., 1979; Fought, John.
  - "Asymmetrical Developments in Language Obsolescence and the Ethnography of Speaking in the Arvanitika Communities in Greece", 1985; Friedl, Ernestine.
  - "Language Relativism and Poetic Language", 1983; Friedrich, Paul, 1927-
  - "Mass Communication Research: State of the Art - Where we are, and Where we should be Going", 1976; Gerbner, George.
  - "Effect of Aphasia on the Retrieval of Lexicon and Syntax", 1976; Goodglass, Harold.
  - "The Strange Saga of Dr. Feckless and Mr. High", Grievanceson, Badlai Lois Fakener.
  - "Can a Language like Newspeak serve the Purposes it Explicitly intends? Now? Never? Not Yet?, Grimshaw, Allen D.
  - "Communicative Nonsuccess: Some Complicating Dimensions", 1981-1982; Grimshaw, Allen D.
  - "Perspective on Discourse: Multi-Disciplinary Study of a Naturally Occurring Conversation" - Prospectus., 1982; Grimshaw, Allen D.
  - "Pragmatics and Linguistics", [1977]; Haberland, Hartmut and Jacob Mey.
  - "Ethics and Professionalism in American Anthropology", 1986; Hakken, David.
  - "On Bonaparte and the Neogrammarians as Field Workers", 1971; Hamp, Eric P.
  - "Some Contexts for Non-Truth Telling in American Culture", 1970; Hogan, Helen.
  - "Introduction" [to Dissertation], n.d.; Irvine, Judith.
  - "A Structural Way of Connecting Language and Culture", 1962; Jacobs, Melville, 1902-1971
  - "Tentative Inferences from debates on Tradition in the Science of Language", [1974]; Jakobson, Roman, 1896-1982
  - "Computers and Culture History: A Glen Canyon Study", 1963; Jennings, Jesse D.
  - "Native Place Names in Alaska: Trends in Policy and Research", 1985; Kari, James.
  - "From Paleogrammarians to Neogrammarians", [1974]; Kiparsky, Paul.
  - "Problems of Time Perspective in Dance and Music", Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - "Introduction: Cultural Anthropology", 1971; Labby, David.
  - "Society in Crisis: Anthropology and the Revolution", 1970; Lancaster, Chet and Jane Lancaster.
  - "The Committee on Research in Native American Languages", 1983; Leeds-Hurwitz, Wendy.
  - "Ethnomethodology and Structuralism: Linguicity and the De-Centering of Core Values", Lemert, Charles C.
  - "Wisdom from the Periphery: Talk, Thought and Politics in the Ethnographic Theater of John Millington Synge", McDermott, R. P.
  - "On Taxi-Cab Speech: What the Dispatcher says to the Drivers", n.d.; Merritt, Marilyn.
  - "Choice and Occasion: Sweet Moments", 1980; Mintz, Sidney Wilfred, 1922-
  - "The Pursuit of Ethnography: The Seduction of Science by Art", [1974]; Parssinen, Carol Ann.
  - "A Problem in the Study of Ideals: Levi-Strauss' Statistical and Mechanical Models.", Peacock, James L.
  - "Humboldt's Description of the Javanese Verb", [1974]; Percival, W. Keith.
  - "Rask's Views of Linguistic Development and Phonetic Correspondences", [1974]; Percival, W. Keith.
  - "Acquisition of Rules for Appropriate Speech Usage", 1970; Philips, Susan U.
  - "Indian Education, Chapters II and V" - ms., [1970]; Philips, Susan U.
  - "L'Utilisation des Ordinateurs en Anthropologie", 1962; Piault, Colette.
  - "Sacred Language: The Nature of Supernatural Discourse in Lakota", 1983; Powers, William K.
  - "Introduction" for Anthropology and Poetry., 1983; Prattis, J. Iain.
  - "An Ethnography of Speaking Among Children on St. Vincent Island", 1975; Ralston, Lenore.
  - "Thoreau's Last Words, and America's First Literatures", 1982; Ramsey, Jarold, 1937-
  - "Theory-Orientation versus Data-Orientation: a Recurrent Theme in Linguistics", [1974]; Robins, R. H.
  - "Racine's World and Theater: A Study of his Translation Methods and their Implications for Theory in General", Romano, Albert J. and Howard Hatton.
  - "Sixteenth and Seventeenth Century Grammars", [1974]; Rowe, John Howland.
  - "The Hui: Proposal for a Socio-Linguistic Analysis of a Maori Social Occasion", 1969; [Salmond, Mary] Anne Thorpe.
  - "Sarcee Myths and Tales"; "Selected Poems"; "A Bird's Eye View of American Languages North of Mexico" --photocopies of outlines., [1939]; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
  - "Muller, Tylor, Darwin: Intellectual Appropriation and Epistemological Schism in Mid-Victorian Thought" - abstract., [1980]; Schrempp, Gregory A.
  - "The Cognitive Interests of the Human Species: Toward a Neo-Marxist Theory of Science and Society", [1971]; Schroyer, Trent.
  - "Units of Discourse in Everyday Speech", 1978; Sherzer, Joel.
  - "Person, number, gender in Chinook", Silverstein, Michael
  - "Wasco Verb Entries" Appendix II, Silverstein, Michael
  - "The Origin and Development of Linguistics in India", [1968]; Staal, J. F.
  - "Introduction" History of Anthropology., 1982; Stocking, George W., 1928-
  - "Automatic Theme Analysis Using Tree Building Procedures", 1962; Stone, Philip J. and Earl B. Hunt.
  - "Problems of Historical Ethnology", n.d.; Sturtevant, William C.
  - "Games as Models of Power", 1981; Sutton-Smith, Brian.
  - "Mythography and Mythopoesis", Tedlock, Dennis.
  - "Science and Swaraj" Conference on Urgent Research in Social Anthropology., 1968; Uberoi, J. P. S.
  - "Language in Action"; "Enige Beschouwingen Over Amerikaanse en Nederlandse Linguistiek", 1966-1967; Uhlenbeck, E. M.
  - "Vicissitudes of Paradigms", [1964]; Verburg, Pieter A.
  - "Lexicostatistics in the Regency Period", n.d.; Wells, Rulon.
  - "Phonemics in the Nineteenth Century, 1876-1900", [1968]; Wells, Rulon.
  - "Archaeological Perspective on Algonkian-Gulf Linguistic Relationships", 1957; Willey, Gordon R.
  - "Anthropology on the Warpath", 1970; Wolf, Eric R. and Joseph G. Jorgensen.
  - "Notes on the Sociology of Knowledge and Linguistics", [1974]; Wolff, Kurt H. and Barrie Thorne.
  - "Dissertation Proposal", n.d.; Wolfson, Nessa.
- Series V. Language in Society, 1968-1992; 37 lin. feet
  Language in Society is an international journal of sociolinguistics concerning all branches of speech and language aspects of social life and was founded by Hymes in 1972. This series contains manuscripts, both accepted and rejected, correspondence, and note cards. The largest series in the collection, it reflects Hymes editorial work in the field of sociolinguistics.
  - Subseries A. Early Correspondence (Box 67-73)
    Correspondence on the initiation of the journal, including the first editorial board. Also includes some general correspondence with Dell Hymes and reviewers of submissions. Arranged alphabetically, then chronologically, some loosely.
    - Abdulaziz, M.H., 1970-1975
    - Akhmanova, Olga, 1971-1973
    - Alexandre, Pierre, 1970-1975
    - Alleyne, Mervin, 1970-1975,1980
    - Brazeau, Jacques, 1970-1971
    - Bright, William, 1970-1976
    - Cambridge University Press, 1971-1992; 7 folders
      - Folder 1, 1971-1972
      - Folder 2, 1973-1975
      - Folder 3, 1976-1977
      - Folder 4, 1978-1979
      - Folder 5, 1980-1984
      - Folder 6, 1985-1989
      - Folder 7, 1990-1992
    - Cazden, Courtney, 1973-1976
    - Conklin, Harold C., 1970
    - Crystal, David, 1970-1974
    - Dalby, David, 1972-1974
    - Danes, Frantisek, 1970-1975
    - Desheriev, J. D., 1974-1976
    - Editorial Board, 1969-1990; 2 folders
      - Folder 1, 1969-1970
      - Folder 2, 1971-1990
    - Ervin-Tripp, Sue, 1974-1975
    - Ferguson, Charles A., 1970-1978
    - Fishman, Joshua, 1968-1975
    - Goffman, Erving, 1973,1976,1979
    - Greimas, A. J., 1970-1975,1980
    - Grimshaw, Allen, 1970-1979
    - Gumperz, John, 1970-1974
    - Hancock, Ian, 1977
    - Haugen, Einar, 1972-1975
    - Hurel, Robert, 1971,1974-1975
    - Hymes, Dell, 1970-1992; 8 folders
      - Folder 1, 1970-1972
      - Folder 2, 1973
      - Folder 3, 1974-1975
      - Folder 4, 1976-1979
      - Folder 5, 1980-1982
      - Folder 6, 1983-1985
      - Folder 7, 1986-1987
      - Folder 8, 1988-1992
    - Ivic, Pavle, 1971,1974-1975
    - Jacobson, Roman, 1971
    - Keenan, Elinor, 1975
    - Kjolseth, Rolf, 1970-1975
    - Labov, William, 1970-1973
    - Lastra de Suarez, Yolanda, 1970-1974
    - Lieberson, Stanley, 1970-1975
    - Mazrui, Ali A., 1970-1975
    - Neustupny, Jiri, 1969-1975
    - Pandit, P. B., 1970,1974-1975
    - Parkin, David J., 1975
    - Pride, John, 1970-1979
    - Reviewers, 1970-1988; 14 folders
      - Folder 1, 1970-1972
      - Folder 2, 1973-1975
      - Folder 3, 1976
      - Folder 4, 1977-1978
      - Folder 5, 1979-1980
      - Folder 6, 1981
      - Folder 7, 1982
      - Folder 8, 1983
      - Folder 9, 1984
      - Folder 10, 1985
      - Folders 11-12, 1986
      - Folder 13, 1987
      - Folder 14, 1988
    - Sack, Fritz, 1971-1974
    - Samarin, William J., 1968-1975
    - Sanches, Mary, 1970-1973
    - Sankoff, Gillian, 1970-1973
    - Schaff, Adam, 1971-1975
    - Schegloff, Emanuel A., 1970-1972
    - Schweizer, Alexander D., 1969-1973
    - Sherzer, Joel, 1972-1974,1980
    - Shuy, Roger, 1973-1974
    - Sibata, Takesi, 1970,1974-1975
    - Steger, Hugo, 1971-1975
    - Szepe, Gyorgy, 1971-1973
    - Trim, J. L. M., 1970-1972
    - Voorhoeve, Jan, 1970-1975
    - Whiteley, Wilfred, 1970-1972
    - Wurm, S. A., 1968-1975
  - Subseries B. Manuscripts, offprints, correspondence
    Loosely arranged alphabetically then chronologically by periodical volume issue.
    - Volume1-Volume 3, 1972-1974 (Box 73)
    - Volume 3, 1974 (Box 74)
    - Volume 4, 1975 (Box 75)
    - Volume 4-Volume 5, 1975-1976 (Box 76)
    - Volume 5, 1976 (Box 77)
    - Volume 5-Volume 6, 1976-1977 (Box 78)
    - Volume 6-Volume 7, 1977-1978 (Box 79)
    - Volume 7, 1978 (Box 80)
    - Volume 7-Volume 8, 1978-1979 (Box 81)
    - Volume 8, 1979 (Box 82)
    - Volume 8-Volume 9, 1979-1980 (Box 83)
    - Volume 9, 1980 (Box 84)
    - Volume 9-Volume 10, 1980-1981 (Box 85)
    - Volume 10-Volume 11, 1981-1982 (Box 86)
    - Volume 11, 1982 (Box 87)
    - Ten Year Index-Volume 12, 1982-1983 (Box 88)
    - Volume 12, 1983 (Box 89)
    - Volume 13, 1984 (Box 90)
    - Volume 13-Volume 14, 1984-1985 (Box 91)
    - Volume 14, 1985 (Box 92)
    - Volume 15, 1986 (Box 93)
    - Volume 15, 1986 (Box 94)
    - Volume 15-Volume 16, 1986-1987 (Box 95)
    - Volume 16-Volume 17, 1987-1988 (Box 96)
    - Volume 18-Volume 19, 1989-1990 (Box 97)
    - Volume 19-Volume 20, 1990-1991 (Box 98)
    - Volume 20-Volume 21, 1991-1992 (Box 99)
  - Subseries C. Rejected manuscripts, correspondence
    Loosely arranged alphabetically then chronologically.
    - Ad-Be, before 1976 (Box 99)
    - Bl-Gr, before 1976 (Box 100)
    - Ha-Mo, before 1976 (Box 101)
    - Mu-Vel, before 1976 (Box 102)
    - Ve-Ya, before 1976 (Box 103)
    - Ab-Ch, 1977 (Box 103)
    - Cu-Ko, 1977 (Box 104)
    - La-Zu, 1977 (Box 105)
    - B-Y, Ag-Clar, 1978,1979 (Box 106)
    - Clau-Go, 1979 (Box 107)
    - Gr-Me, 1979 (Box 108)
    - Mi-St, 1979 (Box 109)
    - Su-Zo, Ad-Be, 1979,1980 (Box 110)
    - Br-Lo, 1980 (Box 111)
    - Mc-Wi, 1980 (Box 112)
    - Ab-La, 1981 (Box 113)
    - Le-Wo, Ad-Be, 1981,1982 (Box 114)
    - Bi-Hi, 1982 (Box 115)
    - Ho-Wa, 1982 (Box 116)
    - Wh-Zu, Ad-Gre, 1982,1983 (Box 117)
    - Gri-Wi, 1983 (Box 118)
    - Al-La, 1984 (Box 119)
    - Ma-Za, 1984 (Box 120)
    - Al-Lo, 1985 (Box 121)
    - Ma-Yu, Al-Be, 1985,1986 (Box 122)
    - Bi-Mu, 1986 (Box 123)
    - Ne-Zu, 1986 (Box 124)
    - Ab-Ly, 1987 (Box 125)
    - Mo-Yo, 1987 (Box 126)
    - Ad-Ja, 1988 (Box 127)
    - Ke-Ts, 1988 (Box 128)
    - Vi-Wi, Al-Hi, 1988,1989 (Box 129)
    - Hu-Ts, 1989 (Box 130)
    - Tw-Zu, Ad-Co, 1989,1990 (Box 131)
    - Da-Lo, 1990 (Box 132)
    - Lu-Yan, 1990 (Box 133)
    - Yon-Zu, Ah-Es, 1990,1991 (Box 134)
    - Fa-Man, 1991 (Box 135)
    - Mar-To, 1991 (Box 136)
    - Uc-Zh, Ad-Zh, 1991,1992 (Box 137)
  - Subseries D. Notecards
    Office card index to published and rejected articles and reviews. Also includes some brief notices and notes on prospective articles. Loosely arranged chronologically.
    - Published articles and reviews, 1972-1992 (Box 138)
    - Rejected manuscripts and reviews, 1972-1992 (Box 139)
    - Brief notices, 1981-1987 (Box 140)
    - Prospective articles, 1987-1992 (Box 140)